<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Downfal of tythes no sacriledge; or Certain earnest and important queries, with their reasons or grounds. In answer to the author of a printed sheet, entituled, An item against sacriledge, or sundry queries concerning tythes. Earnestly tending to a full result, what ought to be done by the now present Parliament concerning tythes. Manifestly proving, that it is no sacriledge for the now present power to remove the laws and authority, whereby tythes, or any other maintenance for the ministery, is informed. Shewing also the dangerous inconveniency that necessarily ensueth, upon forcing maintenance for the ministery, and the unlawfulness of it in the sight of God. By Ellis Bradshaw.</title>
            <author>Bradshaw, Ellis.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77224</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4143</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E714_18</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207248</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866313</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866313</idno>
            <idno type="VID">166713</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77224)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 166713)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 110:E714[18])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Downfal of tythes no sacriledge; or Certain earnest and important queries, with their reasons or grounds. In answer to the author of a printed sheet, entituled, An item against sacriledge, or sundry queries concerning tythes. Earnestly tending to a full result, what ought to be done by the now present Parliament concerning tythes. Manifestly proving, that it is no sacriledge for the now present power to remove the laws and authority, whereby tythes, or any other maintenance for the ministery, is informed. Shewing also the dangerous inconveniency that necessarily ensueth, upon forcing maintenance for the ministery, and the unlawfulness of it in the sight of God. By Ellis Bradshaw.</title>
                  <author>Bradshaw, Ellis.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>6 [i.e. 23], [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for H. Cripps, and L. Lloyd, and are to be sold at their shop in Popes-head Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London; :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Page 23 misnumbered 6.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Octob: 11".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Tithes --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:166713:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Downfal of Tythes no Sacriledge; OR Certain earneſt and important QUERIES, With their Reaſons or Grounds. In anſwer to the Author of a printed ſheet, entitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>An Item againſt Sacriledge, or ſundry Queries concerning TYTHES.</hi> Earneſtly tending to a full Reſult, what ought to be done by the now preſent Parliament concerning Tythes. Manifeſtly proving, that it is no Sacriledge for the now preſent Power to remove the Laws and Authority, whereby Tythes, or any other maintenance for the Miniſtery, is inforced. Shewing alſo the dangerous inconveniency that neceſſarily enſueth, upon forcing maintenance for the Miniſtery, and the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfulneſs of it in the ſight of God. By <hi>Ellis Bradſhaw.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>He that ſoweth to the fleſh, ſhall of the fleſh reap corruption; but he that ſoweth to the ſpirit, ſhall of the ſpirit reap life everlaſting,
<bibl>
                  <hi>Gal. 6.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London;</hi> Printed for <hi>H. Cripps,</hi> and <hi>L. Lloyd,</hi> and are to be ſold at their ſhop in <hi>Popes-head Alley,</hi> 1653.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:166713:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:166713:2"/>
            <head>Certaine earneſt and important <hi>Queries,</hi> with their Reaſons, or Grounds; in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to the Author of a printed ſheet, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled, <hi>An Item againſt Sacriledge, or ſundry Queries concerning Tythes,</hi> earneſtly tending to a full Reſult, what ought to be done by the now preſent Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, concerning Tythes.</head>
            <p>YOu demand, <hi>Whether the Miniſtery of England hath not as good a propriety in Tythes, as Noblemen, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, and Precholders have in their Lands:</hi> the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whereof you render is, becauſe <hi>Ethelwolph ſon of King</hi> Egbert, <hi>who had brought the Saxon Heptarchy into a Monarchy, had all the Lands of</hi> England <hi>for his Demeſne, as it acknowledged by Sir</hi> Edward Cook <hi>in his Commentaries upon</hi> Littletons <hi>Tenures, and conferred the Tythes of all the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome upon the Church by his Royal Charter, dated</hi> Anno 855. <hi>in theſe words,</hi> to wit;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>King</hi> Ethelwolph <hi>by the conſent of Prelates and Princes which ruled in</hi> England, <hi>and under him in their ſeveral Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, did inrich the Church of</hi> England <hi>with the Tythes of all his lands and goods by his Charter Royal, &amp;c. adding in the end, that whoſe ſhould encreaſe the gift, God would pleaſe to proſper and encreaſe his daies, but if any ſhould preſume to dimineſh the ſame, that he ſhould be called to an account for it as Gods Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Seat; and this,</hi> you ſay, <hi>he did not only as Lord Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:166713:3"/>but as Propriator of the whole Land; the Lords and great men at that time having no propriety or eſtates of perma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency, but as accountants to the King, whoſe the whole Land was; and yet they alſo gave their free conſents; which the King requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that thereby they might be barred from pleading any Tenant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, as alſo to oblige them to ſtand in maintenance of Tythes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all pretenders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon theſe premiſes you conclude, <hi>That the people can have no right or propriety in them, for they never bought or paid for them, neither could they come by inheritance; for that which was not their Forefathers, could not deſcend to them, neither came they to them by Donation, which they can never ſhew.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I deſire therefore, and give me leave in love and meekneſs firſt to query.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Query.</hi> Whether you be in good earneſt, yea or no? that upon this guifture of King <hi>Ethelwolph, The Miniſtery of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>have as good a propriety in Tythes, as Noble men, Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and Freeholders have in their Lands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> Conſidering firſt the ground and reaſon why the King gave them, to wit, becauſe he accounted them as a due debt owing to God, and not becauſe they were his own De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſne, and free to be at his own diſpoſing, but he did account them due unto God, <hi>Jure Divino;</hi> and therefore expreſſed himſelf in ſuch prophetical words, to wit, <hi>That whoſe ſhould encreaſe the gift, God would pleaſe to proſper and encreaſe his daies, but if any ſhould preſume to diminiſh the ſame, that he ſhould be called to an account for it at Gods Judgment Seat;</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which obſerve, he did not ſay they ſhould be called to an account before his own Judgment Seat, nor any other civil Judicators, but <hi>before the Judgment Seat of God,</hi> implying, that he did not account it as a matter belonging to him to puniſh them, but to the Lord himſelf, who, in his opinion, required ſuch a part as due to himſelf; ſo that if any ſhould rob him, as <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.8. he expected that the Lord ſhould judg him for that himſelf; as ſo, no doubt but his Prelates; that
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:166713:3"/>(as you ſay) <hi>conſented to the buſineſs,</hi> had admoniſhed him what was his duty in that reſpect, for the doctrine of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates in thoſe daies was, That Tythes were due in every reſpect, conform, and ſuitable to the Judaical Law; as ſo, you ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge and ſay, that <hi>the Text and Body of the Common-Law, affirmes Tythes to be due</hi> Jure Divino, <hi>as Sir</hi> Edward Cook <hi>teſtifies in the ſecond part of his Reports;</hi> ſo that you do acknowledge, and it is the bent and drift of thoſe Queries, to prove the Tythes due to the Miniſtery <hi>Jure Divino.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> But if Tythes be due <hi>Jure Divino</hi> to the Chriſtian Miniſters,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſe.</hi> Then they were due to the Chriſtian Miniſtery be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the time of the ſaid King <hi>Ethelwolph,</hi> and ſo were never his, nor at his diſpoſing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> For if Tythes be due <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> they were the gift of God to the Chriſtian Miniſters, who in all ages have been appointed as his chief receivers of any thing ſanctified, or ſet apart, or given unto God, the Miniſters, I ſay, together with the <hi>poor, the ſtranger, the fatherleſs, and the widdow, are his</hi> Subſtitutes and receivers of what is given to him; and ſo by conſequence they were either due to God, and ſo to the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery, before that free Donation of King <hi>Ethelwolph,</hi> or els they are not due <hi>Jure Divino;</hi> and ſo you loſe the title <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> in pleading the title <hi>Jure humano;</hi> ſo that if the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters title <hi>Jure humano</hi> fall to the ground as unjuſt, or inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, then you loſe them both; as ſo, without all queſtion, if you but derive it from King <hi>Ethelwolph,</hi> it will certainly fall.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> For firſt, if it be examined what he had to do to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriate the free Donation of all the Tythes to himſelf, as if they had been his, and he had given them to the Church, and as if they had not been Gods own proper dues, and ſo due to the Miniſtery and the poor, &amp;c. by the free Donation of the Lord himſelf: I ſhall leave it to the judgment of who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever accounteth them due <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> and refer them to a
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:166713:4"/>text <hi>Levit.</hi> 27. <hi>ver.</hi> 26. whether that which is, or ſhould be the Lords <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> may be ſanctified by man, or given by him, as of his own to give, when it is the Lords already? The words are theſe; to wit, <hi>Only the firſtling of the Beaſts, which ſhould be the Lords firstling, no man ſhall ſanctifie it, whether it be Oxe, or Sheep, it is the Lords;</hi> implying, that it was utterly unlawful for any to aſcribe the ſanctification or free Donation of that unto God, which was his already in juſt propriety, and ſanctified already, as <hi>holy to the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For it is but the ſame caſe, as when a man thinketh to get favour and credit amongſt men, and ſometimes doth ſo, by giving of other mens goods, and by giving men goods, that are their own already.</p>
            <p>For firſt, if the Tythes of <hi>England</hi> were due to God, and ſo to the Miniſtery before <hi>Ethelwolph</hi> gave them, then they were properly alſo their own already, and if he had not given them, he had robbed God, and robbed the Church.</p>
            <p>And if they were not due before he gave them, then the Lord himſelf, nor his faithful Miniſters, have now no title at all to the Tythes of <hi>England,</hi> but derivative from <hi>Ethelwolph, and the ſucceeding Kings, that have confirmed the ſame by</hi> Magna Charta, <hi>and the Lawes of the Land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us then conſider how this King <hi>Ethelwolph</hi> came to be propriate in the Tythes of <hi>England,</hi> and it will appear where the juſt propriety reſteth now, as being the ſame caſe, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of conqueſt.</p>
            <p>For firſt, let me ask, did the inheritors of Lands ſell all their eſtates to the King, or give them to the King, ſo as to make all <hi>England</hi> his own Demeſne, and themſelves but as Stewards, and as accountants to him? he had then indeed a great Demeſne, and in all likelyhood many thouſand Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards.</p>
            <p>But this I am confident that you will not affirm; to wit, that it came to him from the occupiers of Lands, either by purchaſe, or free Donation, to be his own Demeſne: For</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:166713:4"/>
            <p>Though you ſay he had brought the Saxon Heptarchy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Monarchy, yet how he did it you ſay nothing, but refer us to Sir <hi>Edward Cook, and Sir Henry Steelmans Counſels, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi> 855.</p>
            <p>But becauſe I know beforehand, that he could never bring a Heptarchy into a Monarchy, but either by policy or force, or both, I ſhall not take pains to ſearch the Chronologies, but rather aſſume, that he brought it to a Monarchy, and made himſelf an abſolute Monarch, and that by conqueſt, the which I ſhall acknowledge is a lawful title, if on his part the war was juſt.</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſe him the firſt and moſt abſolute Monarch that ever was in <hi>England,</hi> yet I cannot ſee how he could come to be ſo far propriate in the Tythes, as to <hi>confer them on the Church by his Royal Charter,</hi> unleſs we muſt conclude, that they were not due to the Church before to be paid by others, to wit, the owners and occupiers of land.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> For if they were due to be paid by others before he gave them, what thanks to him for his Donation? or how can it be ſaid to be his Donation? for it was not he, but the people that gave them, and that of their own encreaſe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the (Lord) and not the (King) had encreaſed them; and if they gave them freely, as due to God, for the <hi>furtherance of the Goſpel, they had their reward</hi> from the hand of God, and not from the King for any ſuch duties, nor was the King able to give them a ſuitable reward, ſuch as they might expect. See <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.6. and <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.20. and <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.17. and <hi>Prov.</hi> 5.10.</p>
            <p>Nor could they expect any reward at all, if they did but give them, either to pleaſe the King, or becauſe they durſt do no other, fearing his authority, by the Rod of Power ſhaken over them in a compulſive way, for God hath promis'd no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward upon that account.</p>
            <p>Neither could the King expect any reward from God for giving other mens goods, for cutting large, though out of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens hides; as ſo it was, unleſs you will ſay, and ſtand
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:166713:5"/>by it, that there was no Tythe due to be paid by them, till the King had given it, and that his title by Conqueſt was ſo large and ample, as that they had no propriety in the Land at all, but what he freely gave them, or ſold them, &amp;c. all which if you affirm, I deſire you to conſider the dangerous conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences that muſt neceſſarily follow, if that ſhould be ſo, which yet I cannot believe that you will affirm; to wit.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Conſeq.</hi> Firſt, it muſt neceſſarily follow, that every Conqueror of Land or Nation, or every Purchaſor of land, where Tythes are not payable by Civil Right, hath the full propriety of the Tythe thereof at his own diſpoſing; and that as hath been ſaid, the Tythes, nor any part thereof are due to God, nor to his receivers, to be paid by the occupiers of lands, but the Conquerors may exact them; and it were not a robbing of God, nor his Church, if the Conqueror do exact and take them to himſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> For what he may give to another that is not due to be given, he may take it to himſelf, if he ſo pleaſeth, or he may give it to any whom he approveth of, as Miniſters of Chriſt; and ſo if he give it for maintenance of Jeſuites and Popiſh Prieſts, as ſo in all likelyhood he will, if he be a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt; and ſo in like caſe of whatever opinion a Conqueror is of, all his whole Nation muſt be ſteered by him, and act in Religion according to his conſcience; and not their own, and ſo in all likelyhood ſhould all be inforced to maintain a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery againſt their conſciences, whom they know they ought not to receive to houſe, neither bid them Godſpeed, leaſt they be partakers of their evil deeds, See <hi>John</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>And remember for this Queen <hi>Maries</hi> daies, and others daies beſides; and ſo by that means they may damn their own and their childrens ſouls, of which you cannot deny but they are guilty, if they do periſh by that means.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Conſeq.</hi> It quite contradicteth the very end of theſe your Queries, which are chiefly to prove, that Tythes are due to the Miniſters <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> the which they cannot be,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:166713:5"/>if they were not not due before that King gave them; as hath been proved.</p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Conſe.</hi> It would alſo follow (not only) that the Church or Miniſtry, no nor the Lord himſelf had any title to the Tithes, till the King had given it them; But alſo that till every King or Conquerer, or Governours whomſoever, have confirmed al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo <hi>the Laws of the Land, and Magna Charta,</hi> all title thereunto <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> is as out of date, and ſo by conſequence now for the preſent, till this preſent Power have given them alſo to the Church; the title <hi>Jure Divino</hi> is not in force, but they may diſpoſe of them, as they think beſt, as to whom they ſhall account of as the Lords Receivers, that have the beſt proprieties in their opinions for receiving Tythes or Church maintenance, and if they do it not it is their ſin.</p>
            <p n="4">4 <hi>Conſe.</hi> It would alſo follow, that all ſorts of Tradeſmen and Merchants are not bound at all, as well as Occupiers of Lands, either to give a tenth, or a liberall part of that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the Lord hath increaſed them: Becauſe it was never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirable by the Laws of the Land, and <hi>Magna Charta.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereas this I am certain, and can make it ſo appear both from the Moral Law, and the Goſpel alſo, that a tenth of their increaſe is as well due, and paiable, as it is from the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiers of Lands, and Tenements; as I ſhall, if need be, make it to appear, that both are alike, one as the other.</p>
            <p n="5">5 <hi>Conſeq.</hi> It would likewiſe follow, that the now preſent Power, if they think it good, may bring Tythes into a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Treaſury, and reduce the Miniſters to ſtipends: againſt which you have fifteen Queries propoſed, as ſo many Items, or warnings againſt ſuch kind of Sacriledg: ſo that if the Tythes belong to the Civil Power, to be at their diſpoſing by the Laws of the Land; then they may uſe them at their own diſcretion, and diſpoſe them unto Miniſters, as they think convenient. But if they be but due, by the Law of God; then the Civil Power hath no propriety in them at all, nor any thing at all to do, to take them in Cuſtody; or the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:166713:6"/>diſpoſal of them, leſt they rob God.</p>
            <p n="6">6 <hi>Conſeq.</hi> It would likewiſe follow, that all Impropria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that have been moſt ſacriledgiouſly robbed from the Church, in old time, which the Laws of the Land cannot poſſibly recover to the Church again, but men and their heires have a title to it, by the Laws of the Land, as a juſt Inheritance, muſt ſtill ſo continue as their own propriety, and the preſent Power muſt needs be limited to the preſent Laws, and muſt not adventure to take away their proprieties, no more then the Miniſters, which are both confirmed by the Laws of the Land, one as well as the other: Whereas it is not unlawfull even to <hi>Break the jawes of the wicked, and pull the ſpoil out of their teeth:</hi> See <hi>Iob</hi> 29, 17.</p>
            <p>And therefore I demand, in caſe where Tythes are Impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priate, what ought to be done by the preſent Power? to wit:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Query.</hi> Whether they ought not to take off that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſive Power, whereby Impropriators inforce the payment of Tythes to them, that are due by the Law of God, to the Miniſtry, that ſo the Chriſtian people may have their own at their own diſpoſing; that they might be in their own Power, as in the primitive times, <hi>Act.</hi> 5.4.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Conſidering that ſome hold Tythes by the Laws of the Land, as their own Inheritance, being purchaſed for them, by their predeceſſors, and left to them as good, and lawfull, and proper Inheritance, by the Laws of the Land; ſo that whiles the Laws are in force, they cannot poſſibly be taken from them, but are their legal right:</p>
            <p>And, 2. Conſidering, that what ever Lands are ſubject to Tything, they were firſt of all ſubjected thereunto under the notion of duties required by the Goſpel, as due to their Miniſters, who claimed and received them in the Name of Chriſt, as due to him, and ſo by conſequence to them his Miniſters; and that in every reſpect conform and ſuitable to what the Lord required of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> people, to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:166713:6"/>be given to the <hi>Levites:</hi> Which Tythes might <hi>not be chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, nor redeemed, but they muſt add the fift part to it, for all the Tyths of the Land, whether of the ſeed of the Land, or of the fruit of the Tree, was the Lords, holy unto the Lord:</hi> See <hi>Levit.</hi> 27, 30, 31, 32, 33.</p>
            <p>And ſo being none of there own, they had nothing to do to ſell it away, nor to <hi>eat it within their Gates, but muſt bring it to the place which the Lord ſhould chuſe to put his Name there, and there they might eat it together, with the Prieſts, and their Houſholds before the Lord:</hi> Though in caſe they live too remote, <hi>they might turn it into mony, and bring it in their hands:</hi> See <hi>Deut.</hi> 14.22, 23, 24, 25, 26. But then they muſt <hi>beſtow ſo much mony upon Ox, or ſheep, or Wine, or ſtrong Drink, to eat there,</hi> &amp;c. From whence I argue, That.</p>
            <p>If the owners might not <hi>ſell them, nor alien them, or change</hi> or pervert them to any other uſe, but ſuch as the Lord ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed them;</p>
            <p>And if the firſt paying of Tythes in England, was upon this account, as hath been ſaid;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Querie.</hi> Is it not a certain conſequence, that whoever ſold them, or perverted the uſe of them, contrary to the Doctrine which they had then received, were certainly no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then Theeves, and Robbers; and that of the Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: nor were no better accounted of by the Miniſters and generality of Chriſtians in thoſe times, who did account them ſacrilidgeous Theeves:</p>
            <p>And without all queſtion there was never any of the own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Lands, that ever ſold the Tythe of their Land to their Lords or Patrons: But it was the Patrons of Tythes that were intruſted, and impowered for inſtallment of Miniſters, that ſold them, or perverted them to their own uſe, as it pleaſed themſelves, having Power in their hands, and neither fearing God, nor reverencing man, they exerciſed tyranny: and ſo their poſterities after them, have done the like by their example: And this being ſo, let all men judg whether
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:166713:7"/>this was not Robbery: and whether ſuch who bought them as an Inheritance; and ſuch, who kept them, or keep them yet, are not as bad as they; Seeing receivers in Law, and Juſtice both, are as bad as Theeves: And they that have made Laws whereby they hold them, and pleaded their cauſes in ſuits of Law, to inforce their Payment, were little better.</p>
            <p>And it being an approved maxim, both in Law, and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; That whatſoever is ſtolen, or wrongfully wreſted, from the right owners, can never be juſtly, and honeſtly kept, by any poſterity, or ſucceſſive heir, that ſhall ſucceed, though never ſo many Generations after: For they are no better then were receivers of Robbed Inheritance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Query.</hi> I therefore deſire to know, if any can ſhew that either Kings, or Patrons, or Landlords whomſoever, had ever any right or proper title, to any Tythes in England, ſuch as to ſell them from the Church; or give them either, or take them to themſelves: And then I ſhall confeſs, that if ſuch King or Patron, or Land lord whomſoever, gave them to the Church; It is proper ſacriledge in who ever tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them from the Church again by force, or falſhood, But if they cannot, I deſire to know whether they would deſire the now preſent Power, to confirm ſuch Laws whereby Theeves and Robbers may force the payment of ſuch Impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priate Tythes, yea, or no: And I ſhall deſire to know upon</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Query.</hi> What Scripture ground the now preſent Power may build their Faith, to compell any man to pay his Tythes, though to the very Miniſters of Chriſt themſelves; ſuch who are known by their Fruites, to be his Miniſters: Yea though the preſent Power ſhould acknowledge them to be due, and that they ought to be payd; conſidering theſe enſuing reaſons;</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe they cannot prove that Civil Power hath any title to them, or any propriety in them, as hath been ſaid;</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>Reaſ.</hi> For how can Kings, or Landlords be ſo far pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priate in them as to ſell them to men, or give them to God,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:166713:7"/>when it is not denyed but that Tythes were all due unto God before, if they be due? unleſs we ſhould ſay, they had conquer'd the Land from the Lord himſelf, and given him a Tenth to live on, and to maintain his Miniſters; which were blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to affirm:</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Reaſ.</hi> For this would be the reſult, whereas whoever conquered it, or obtained any juſt propriety to any of the Lands, it was by his Providence, or as a free Donation, as I hope none will deny; <hi>For the Earth is the Lords, and the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs thereof,</hi> Pſalm.</p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Reaſ.</hi> For then by conſequence the Kings and Landlords, or any civil Power, may expect all the rewards, and they that give them, muſt expect nothing at all, by way of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards from the hand of God; in regard they give but that which was another mans, and not in their Power to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold; Whereas God hath promiſed, they that <hi>communicate liberally, and make them that teach them partakers with them in all good things; they ſhall reap liberally.</hi> See <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.6. &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In regard of the evil conſequences, that muſt neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly follow, to wit;</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, Becauſe, If the Rod of Power be generally held forth, for inforcement of all, to pay their Tythes, to ſuch as procure inſtallment, by the civil Power, eſpecially in caſe when ſuch prove bad, and enemies of God;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſeq.</hi> They may force them to pay them to <hi>Theeves and Robbers,</hi> and ſuch as <hi>enter not by the Door, (which is Chriſt himſelf:)</hi> See <hi>John</hi> 10.1, 7. And ſuch as are <hi>Hirelings, and care not for the Sheep, but come</hi> purpoſely <hi>to ſteal, and to kill, and to deſtroy you;</hi> ſuch as will <hi>not ſtrengthen the diſeaſed, nor heal the ſick, nor bind up that which was broken, nor bring again that which was loſt; but with force and violence, they will</hi> ſeek to <hi>rule them.</hi> See <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34.4. They will not, like <hi>Paul, nouriſh them with meekneſs, as a nurſe cheriſheth her children;</hi> they will not <hi>become all things, unto all men, that by all means they might ſave ſome:</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:166713:8"/>
            <p>As I might largely inſtance in many other particulars; whereby they may eaſily be diſcerned, as Chriſt hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, and given us notice how to <hi>know them by their, fruits,</hi> as ſo <hi>the ſheep of Chriſt</hi> for the moſt part do.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> But if <hi>evil ſhepherds, and Theeves, and Wolves,</hi> may be <hi>known by their fruits:</hi> And if we ought to <hi>beware of,</hi> and not maintain them, leſt we be <hi>partakers of there evil deeds;</hi> See 2 <hi>John</hi> 10.11.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>Conſeq.</hi> Then it neceſſarily followeth, that ſuch com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſion to the paying of Tythes in ſuch caſes, is an abſolute compulſion, to the doing that which is abſolutely forbidden by the holy Ghoſt;</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Conſeq.</hi> And they that thus compel them, are chiefly guilty of that very ſin, though the people that obey them cannot be clear, but they <hi>are partakers of their evil deeds.</hi> See</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John</hi> 10.11.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> For if it be unlawful to <hi>receive them to houſe, or bid them Godſpeed</hi> leſt we <hi>be partakers of their evil deeds;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſeq.</hi> Then it is much more unlawful, to give them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant maintenance as Miniſters of Chriſt; and as acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging them ſuch, when it may be we know them to be <hi>Miniſters of Satan,</hi> and Antichriſt; <hi>unholy men, and ſuch as turn the grace of God into wantonneſs, &amp;c.</hi> See <hi>Jude.</hi> 4. to 20.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conclu.</hi> Whom we ought not to maintain either by Tythes or any other portion, or part of maintenance in any kind: No, nor to <hi>bid them</hi> ſo much as <hi>Godſpeed,</hi> or the leaſt countenance in <hi>there evil deed;</hi> So that all forecd mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, either by Tythes, or otherways, produceth this great inconveniency, to the people of God, and is therefore un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful to be thus appointed by the civil State.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Conſeq.</hi> And again, of how dangerous a conſequence were it in caſe the civil State, or Patrons, or Landlords, or Impropriators, prove ſo bad, and oppreſſive as, many have done, to wit, to take all to themſelves, and never care (at all)
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:166713:8"/>to provide Miniſters either good or bad, yet exact the Tythes to a peny as due to them; So that the poor Husbandman hath nothing left him <hi>to give to theſe that are Miniſters in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed,</hi> as it is ſaid concerning <hi>Widows.</hi> See 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.3, 16, 17.18.</p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Conſeq.</hi> And again, another very great and evil conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence will certainly follow, by ſuch compulſion, the which I beleeve hath never yet been taken notice of by any oppoſer of Tythes, or forced maintenance; and that is this, to wit, It is a great ſcandal, yea ſhame, and reproach to any Chriſtian Nation, or to any Chriſtian Church, or particular perſon, that profeſſeth Chriſtianity, to be ſo unrighteous, or ſhew themſelves ſo manifeſtly covetous, and ſo cold in love, and ſo abſolutely diſobedient to the Law of God, and the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, (which is the law of love,) and ſo unſubmiſſive to the Goſpel of Chriſt; yea ſo unfaithfull in beleeving his promiſes; in caſe they be obedient, that they ſhall receive a reward ſutable to their <hi>ſowing to the Spirit:</hi> See <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.6. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.11, 12, 13. That there can hardly be a greater re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach and ſcandal caſt upon them; then that it ſhould ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, that they need compulſion in ſuch a caſe; for of all other ſins, Coveteouſneſs is the moſt odious in the ſight of God, and men; in ſo much, that it is ſpoken of by the Holy Ghoſt, as a note of abſolute wickedneſs, to <hi>bleſs the Covetous, whom,</hi> ſaith the Scripture, <hi>the Lord abhors:</hi> See <hi>Pſalm</hi> 10.3.</p>
            <p>So that it is a juſt ground for all other Churches, and Chriſtian Nations, to abhor us for it, if we appear to be ſo covetous; and they do but follow the Lords own example in ſo doing; And they ought not to be accounted of, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived as Chriſtians; but as Heathens, and Publicans; nor to be communicated with as Chriſtians that appear to be ſuch: <hi>See</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.11. But to be acounted of as yet without: <hi>See</hi> Verſ. 12.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> But if a general compulſion, or conſtraint, be uſed, ſo as none dares deny; how can it appear, that any doth it
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:166713:9"/>freely, but are, together with the reſt of the wickedly covet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, conſtrained alſo: for whiles the Rod of Power, and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Authority, is held over all in general, and all alike, ſo as none dares deny, but doth it readily, how can it appear that any doth it freely, and as a fruit of love, and obedience unto God and dutiful reſpect to the Miniſters of Chriſt, in truth and verity?</p>
            <p>And <hi>Solomon</hi> hath a wiſe ſaying, to wit, <hi>Righteouſneſs ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celleth a Nation, but ſin is a ſhame unto any people,</hi> Prov. 14.24.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſeq.</hi> Therefore it followeth, that it is a ſhame for any Chriſtian people, to ſin ſo injuriouſly againſt God himſelf, and the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and his expreſs commands by his word, and Spirit, to neglect ſuch duties of love and Honour to his faithful Embaſſadors: And more eſpecially (now) when we make profeſſion of a full Reformation, and have covenanted ſo to do: And therefore whoſoever is acceſſary, or hath any hand either in petitioning for, or in giving his hands or voyce for continuance or eſtabliſhment of ſuch compulſive means for Miniſters maintenance, is without all queſtion an efficient cauſe, both of a generall ſin, yea a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional ſin: And of a general, National, and particular re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, and ſhame, and diſhonour to all our Chriſtian Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Churches, and perſons, that by Authority and Power are ſo ingaged; as hath been clearly proved from the Word of truth, ſufficiently to convince any rational creatures that will conſider it, if he beleeves the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> But it will yet be objected, that there will greater ſins, and worſe conſequences, and greater ſhame and reproach follow, if the compulſive Power be taken away; for then it will follow, that Miniſters ſhall want maintenance, for few will give any thing, if they may but chuſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>Anſ.</hi> I anſwer, If it ſhould ſo fall, that were not the fault of the Civil Power, but of their own ſelves, that did neglect their duty:</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:166713:9"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> For it is no where required, in all the whole Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that the Magiſtrate ſhould compel men, to any ſuch duties; but only command, and exhort them, and then the charge lieth at there own door, and the Magiſtrate is clear:</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Anſ.</hi> It is an uncharitable cenſure, to conclude ſo far as that the faithfull Miniſters of Chriſt ſhall want, and that few will give them any thing, if they may but chuſe;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> For firſt, I nothing doubt, but ſuch who are ſent of God, the Lord himſelf will care for, that they ſhall either not want any outward maintenance, or be content to <hi>want as well as to abound,</hi> when he ſeeth it good ſo to excerciſe their faith, as ſo the Apoſtle had learned.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And ſecondly, I cannot beleeve but that all True-heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and faithful Chriſtians, that either feare God, or reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence men, will be the more liberal when the Compulſive Power is taken away; and that according likewiſe as they abound in liberality, God will bleſs them ſo much the more abundantly; ſo that they ſhall ſtill be increaſed, and the more able, by how much more they are more abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly liberal. 2 <hi>Cer.</hi> 9.10, 11, 12. &amp; <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And thirdly, As the duty lyeth not only upon Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandmen but upon all ſorts of Chriſtians to communicate liberally as the <hi>Lord increaſeth them;</hi> I make no doubt but when they know their duty, they will be the more liberal by how much the more ſlack they ſhall find others that are not yet Chriſtianized, nor have attained as yet, either to the love or honour of God or man, nor to beleeve the Scriptures, to wit, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. &amp; 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="4">4. And fourthly, why ſhall ſuch men be compeled to communicate, when the caſe is ſo with them, as that they neither beleeve nor can expect a reward from the hands of God, for ſuch communicating, as ſo they cannot if they do it not freely, but be meerly compeled, and ſo that ſuch communicating is utterly loſt, and therefore
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:166713:10"/>is wrongfully taken, and wreſted from them.</p>
            <p n="5">5. It is a groſs diſparagment to the true Chriſtians of any Church, or Nation that either they are too few, to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a Miniſtry, or too ſpairing, if all they have will ſerve the turn, ſeeing Chriſt hath promiſed to increaſe them accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly and that they ſhall not want, if they be but obedient to do their dutys liberally, as he hath appointed them, in communicating <hi>Carnals,</hi> to the Miniſters of <hi>Spirituals: Gal.</hi> 6.6.</p>
            <p n="6">6. It is a diſparagment to their faith in that they dare not truſt God, but their own Providence: <hi>(to the faith of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple)</hi> if they do not communicate; and <hi>(to the faith of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters)</hi> if they uſe any force.</p>
            <p n="7">7. It is a great diſhonour to Miniſters, if they either in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force them, or receive them of ſuch who need inforcement: <hi>Abraham,</hi> would have ſcorned it, leſt they ſhould ſay they had made him rich.</p>
            <p n="8">8. It is a great diſhonour to Chriſtianity, for they loſe the Honour of doing it freely, if compulſion be uſed in a general way, for they that are Chriſtians indeed, and can do it freely, and faithfully alſo; truſting in God, as ſo he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth of them: yet they cannot in that be diſtinguiſhed from others, that are meerly inforced, I mean in the ſight of men, who cannot know their hearts; in ſuch a caſe when allare alike under compulſive Power, ſo that men may ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count them as covetous, and unfaithful as thoſe who are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peled.</p>
            <p n="9">9. It is a great diſhonour, and a manifeſt afront to the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God; and the Lord Jeſus Chriſt: For thoſe in Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to uſe any inforcement for the maintenance of his Miniſters without commiſſion from him: It is as much as to ſay they are wiſer then God:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> For he never appointed them any other maintenance but what was given freely, no not in the time of the Law; but told them their duties, if they would be bleſſed what
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:166713:10"/>they muſt do by way of Gratitude unto him, for his free do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation both of Land it ſelf, and of the increaſe thereof which was by his bleſſing, and providence and that they ſhould give it <hi>to the Preiſts</hi> as his ſpecial ſubſtitutes <hi>that ſo they might cauſe the bleſsing to reſt upon their Houſe, and all that they had.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But he never required the Magiſtrate to compel them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to theſe duties which are properly to himſelf, no more then to pray, or to offer Sacrifice; all of which were always left to their free wills, to do, or not do, after they were once in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed that it was their duties, ſave only by incitements in the Name of God, which was all the inforcements that ever was uſed, or commanded to be uſed, in the name of men by the Jewiſh Nation.</p>
            <p>However, I grant, that what the Lord commands, it is likewiſe Lawful for the Magiſtrate to command in the name of the Lord; as ſo <hi>Abraham</hi> did, and other Rulers alſo: but not to compel without his commiſſion any ſuch duty, for in ſo doing we both diſhonour his Name, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parage his wiſdom, and take his Name in vain; and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſo cauſe others to do the like:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> For he that inforceth any thing to be given unto God without his commiſſion; he forceth it properly to be given to himſelf, whom they only obey in ſuch Donation and only give it for his ſake; ſo that no rewards can be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pective from God, for ſuch Donations but from him only. And ſo the caſe is the ſame in point of Worſhip: for the Worſhip tendred, or offered unto God, either for fear of men, or for favor, reſpect, or praiſe of men: Is offered unto men, and not to God; and ſo is an Idolizing of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and fearing, or honouring, or reſpecting of it: <hi>more then the Creator himſelf, who is eternally bleſſed,</hi> and that <hi>for evermore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay any ſuch compulſion, is a manifeſt, and wilful in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forcement to the practiſe of Hypocriſie, which is an odious ſin, in the ſight of God, and a manifeſt breach of the nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:166713:11"/>part of the third Commandment. See <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.7. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1. &amp; 5.23. Let ſuch look to it, who are forward to compel unto ſuch duties: For the Lord our God, will not hold them guiltleſs, that either take themſelves, or force others to take his Name in vain.</p>
            <p>Theſe are words, as I ſuppoſe, both of truth and faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; <hi>whether men will hear, or whether they will forbear that are of the rebelious houſe.</hi> See <hi>Ezek.</hi> 2.5, 6, 7. &amp; 3.7, 8, 9.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> But becauſe I am not ignorant but that ſome of thoſe who are eminent in profeſſion, will account me their enemy becauſe I write theſe things, and becauſe they fear the event and ſucceſs will be evil for the Miniſters, if it ſhould be thus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> I Anſwer, in the words of Chriſt, <hi>fear not little flock, it is your Fathers good pleaſure to give you the Kingdom;</hi> if you be of that <hi>little flock</hi> for whom the Kingdom is provid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, what need you fear, though you fear the burthen of main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance for the Miniſtry, ſhall all be layd upon your ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders? Nay though it ſhould be ſo indeed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> For was it not ſo in the Primitive times, and yet <hi>there was none that lacked;</hi> And when the Apoſtles were <hi>ſent forth without bag, or ſcrip, or mony; they lacked nothing;</hi> Nor when they were ſent <hi>into all the world, into all Nations</hi> amongſt hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, and ſtrangers, and of ſtrange languages, yet God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for them.</p>
            <p>And ſo he will do for you, if you can but truſt in him; for it is <hi>he that hath ſaid, I will not fail thee, neither forſake thee;</hi> and this Promiſe is yours, therefore you need not fear, if you be his.</p>
            <p>And beſides, thoſe who are of the ſheep of Chriſt, whether they be Miniſters or of the meaneſt of his flock they may juſtly ſay with <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 23.1. <hi>The Lord is my ſhepard:</hi> And then if they can beleeve as <hi>David</hi> did, they may thence conclude with <hi>David,</hi> to wit, <hi>I ſhall not want:</hi> which is a concluſion that the greateſt Monarch in all the World can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:166713:11"/>poſſibly make from any worldly eſtate be it what it can. And the promiſe is cleere and large, that <hi>he that ſoweth libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, ſhall alſo reap liberally;</hi> and that not only Temporals, but Eternals. See 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. throughout. &amp; <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.6, to 11. And there is a reaſon rendered, to wit, both becauſe <hi>God is able to make all grace to abound to themwards,</hi> that are <hi>Richly liberal;</hi> to give them an <hi>all ſufficient</hi> ſtore of <hi>all things needful,</hi> that ſo <hi>they may abound in every good work.</hi> See 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.8.9. And he is likewiſe willing, for <hi>he that Miniſtreth ſeed to the ſower, will likewiſe Miniſter bread for food, and mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiply their ſeed ſown, and increaſe the fruits of their Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs.</hi> See <hi>Verſ.</hi> 10.11.</p>
            <p>From all which it is manifeſt, that giving to the poor, and communicating to the Miniſtry, are both held forth, and taught by the Apoſtle by the ſame ſimilitude of ſowing, and reaping; And the promiſe, and threatening is alike for both; for they are both accounted under the ſame notion as don, or not don, to the Lord himſelf; who is both able, and will certainly reward us liberally, or ſparingly, as we ſow this way, ſo that we need not fear if we can but claim, and apply his promiſes, and repoſe therein, but we ſhall reap as liberally, as we can poſſibly ſow, if we do it freely, for the caſe is ſo in this as it was with the Apoſtle in reſpect of preaching: If (ſaith he) <hi>I do this thing willingly, I have a reward; but if againſt my will, a diſpenſation of the Goſpel is committed unto me.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.17.</p>
            <p>For if we <hi>ſow liberally,</hi> and do it willingly, we have a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; <hi>but if againſt our wills</hi> there is none promiſed, though it lyeth as a duty Incumbent upon us; to do it however: <hi>and wo unto us if we do it not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For it is eaſie to prove that liberal diſtribution, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication is a morral duty that God requireth of us: And that he will moſt certainly, and ſeverely puniſh us if we do neglect it;</p>
            <p>Though I dare not undertake to prove it moral that we
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:166713:12"/>are ſtinted to a tenth part, as ſome have endeavoured.</p>
            <p>For I can ſooner prove, that all that we have is a morral duty, to give unto God, when need requireth; and that he calleth for it, then any can prove that a tenth is requireth as his ſtinted due.</p>
            <p>But the rule is this, either, to wit, <hi>Every man according as he purpoſeth or (wiſheth) in his heart, ſo let him give not grudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly nor of neceſsity for God loveth a cheerful giver.</hi> See 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.7. The Apoſtle would neither have them neceſſitated to it by compulſion, nor to give it ſomuch as <hi>grudgingly</hi> but in a free loving, and cheerful manner ſo as the Lord may love them in ſo doing, and bleſs them abundantly for it; yea that in ſo doing, they might ſhew the <hi>ſincericy of their love.</hi> See 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.8. the which they could not do if they ſhould be compelled: For what ſhew can be made of love by doing that whereto we are compeled.</p>
            <p>But I muſt not inlarge any further at preſent either to prove the morrality of liberal communication, and diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as I hope God willing to do ere long; nor yet to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer oblections of which there is many; and many devices to propriate Tythes in the hands of the Incumbent: ſome pleading it from the Law of God; But others only from the Laws of the Land; as a Civil right; By which they do ſo lumble the titles together, that they loſe them both, as to the ſtating of incumbents in propriety of them, or Impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priators either; and ſo I hope they will fall into the proper hands of the <hi>Land holders;</hi> that ſo they may have their own at their own diſpoſing, which will be very much; If it pleaſeth God to incline the hearts of the now preſent Power, to abrogate ſuch Laws whereby Tythes are inforced, either to be paid to the Miniſtry, or to Impropriators; who have too long injoyed ſacriligious Inheritance; And too much likewiſe, if it be true as ſome affirm, to wit, That <hi>Impropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations are judged to be twiſe ſo much in value, as all the Perſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and Vicarages that are in Miniſters hands;</hi> And that <hi>the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:166713:12"/>value of them after ten years purchaſe would amount to eight Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All which if juſtly propriate in the hands of the owners would inable them ſufficiently to maintain the Miniſtry, and the poor beſides; and to ſupply the wants of all poor places that in barren Countrys are not able to maintain them; Some rich Pariſhes being <hi>valued to be worth two Thouſand a Year:</hi> The Lord grant our now preſent Parliament, corrage, and wiſedom to abrogate all Laws whereby Iniquity is eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. See <hi>Pſal.</hi> 94.20.</p>
            <p>For it hath long time layne as a ſhame, and diſhonour upon the ſupream Power, and Authority of this Nation, that ſuch manifeſt Robbery hath been not only tolerated but maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Law againſt juſtice, and Righteouſneſs; which is above the Laws as being the end of the Laws: and therefore ought to be the ends of all that are in Autnority: So that if they cannot by Laws accompliſh juſtice, ſo as to <hi>break the laws of the wicked, and pull the prey out of their Teeth,</hi> they ought to do it by Power. See <hi>Job</hi> 29.17.</p>
            <p>The Lord grant that our preſent Power may <hi>put on Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and be clothed with it:</hi> and that there <hi>Judgment may be as a Robe, and a Diamond:</hi> That ſo the God of juſtice may bleſs, and proſper them in their great affairs that concern this life, and may eſtabliſh their Souls in the full propriety of eternal happineſs in the life to come. See <hi>Job.</hi> 29.14.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
